<body>
<head>Introducing Objectification: when is an <ref target="https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-object.html">&lt;object&gt;</ref> a <ref target="https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-place.html">&lt;place&gt;</ref>?</head>
<p> The TEI Guidelines recently (as of TEI P5 version 3.5.0, January 2019) added elements for describing objects and
            encoding the names of objects. These elements include: <ref target="https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-objectName.html">objectName</ref>, <ref target="https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-object.html">object</ref>, <ref target="https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-listObject.html">listObject</ref>
<ref target="https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-objectIdentifier.html">objectIdentifier</ref>,
            as well as changes to many other elements to loosen their descriptions slightly. This paper will introduce these new
            elements to TEI users who many not have had the chance to use them yet, as well as introduce potential uses for the
            encoding of object descriptions in TEI files. </p>
<p>The paper will not, however, merely introduce these elements, but will also look at changes still to be done in the
            TEI Guidelines to fully support the description of objects. For example, much of the <ref target="https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-object.html">object</ref> description content
            model is taken wholesale from that for describing manuscripts. The <ref target="https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-objectIdentifier.html">objectIdentifier</ref> was
            based on the <ref target="https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-msIdentifier.html">msIdentifier</ref> (with some important changes), and <ref target="https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-object.html">object</ref> still has elements like
               <ref target="https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-msContents.html">msContents</ref> in its
            content model. There are many changes that are still needed and this paper actively seeks to involve the community in
            designing these changes. </p>
<p>Changes are not only required to existing content models of elements, but also to clarify the semantics of the
            distinctions between elements. Using examples of large objects such as the Central Library of the National Autonomous
            University of Mexico (UNAM) (c.f. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Central_Library_(UNAM)">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Central_Library_(UNAM)</ref>), which has substantial and important mosaics on its
            external walls, this paper will ask where the border lines are between what one might consider an <ref target="https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-object.html">object</ref> and what might instead
            be encoded as a <ref target="https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-place.html">place</ref>.
            Concluding that the difference lies in the markup intent (as with so much in the TEI), this paper draws a distinction
            between encoding for object description, and geo-political entities.</p>
</body>