<body>
<head>Growing collections of TEI texts: Some lessons from SARIT</head>
<p>Patrick McAllister
                (patrick.mcallister@oeaw.ac.at)</p>
<p>There is no certainty as to the size that a corpus of Indic texts would have, but it
                is certain that this is due, mainly, to its sheer extent, rather than to other
                factors like the frequent reappearance of lost works or of important new witnesses
                to existing ones. Any fancy about the constitution of a corpus of Indic texts,
                however narrowly defined, is quickly sobered by the recognition that such a project
                lies far beyond the capacity of a single generation of scholars. </p>
<p>Nevertheless, some attempts towards its realization do exist, as do very different
                ideas of how such a growing collection should be designed and how it could be
                maintained. The problems that all such attempts must overcome are not only
                technical, but often practical. For example, the common expectation that texts in a
                collection should be consistent at least in their formal characteristics can easily
                conflict with the highly specialized and sometimes changing interests of the
                scholars producing an edition of a work, or also with the fact that individual
                sections of a single work are often edited by different scholars working with
                varying methods. </p>
<p>This talk will reflect on the choices made in SARIT (<ref target="http://sarit.indology.info/">http://sarit.indology.info</ref>), which
                attempts to provide an environment for an expanding collection of Indic texts. The
                proposed solution was, and with some modifications still is, to design a repository
                that, over the very long term, can increase and deepen in such a way that new
                contributions either improve the existing material, or expand the collection with
                new material without disrupting the general integrity and basic standards of such a
                collection.</p>
</body>