<body>
<div org="uniform" part="N" sample="complete">
<head>Recreating history through events</head>
<p part="N">Events are a feature of life in space and time and hence are frequently encountered in
            witnesses of the human culture.</p>
<p part="N">Coming from diverse backgrounds within the TEI based realm of scholarly editing, the
            authors identified a common practice in digital editions for encoding events: dateable
            events are commonly recorded and marked up using e.g. simple <tag scheme="TEI">date when="*"</tag> structures.
            To date, there is no easy single solution to model events that include basic other event
            features, mainly referring back to the questions of <emph>what</emph> happened <emph>when</emph> and with
            <emph>whom</emph>/<emph>what</emph> as subjects and objects of any given event.</p>
<p part="N">There are numerous examples from generically and disciplinarily varying editions where a
            unified way of describing events could provide added value. Our showcase examples
            feature material as diverse as <list rend="inline">
<label>a)</label>
<item>a medieval itinerary and medieval calendars, </item>
<label>b)</label>
<item>an Austrian author’s diary from the 1950s, </item>
<label>c)</label>
<item>a corpus of governmental minutes from the Habsburg empire and </item>
<label>d)</label>
<item>16th century political correspondence.</item>
</list> We will propose a common strategy on how to encode events in a way that can be
            easily parsed and extracted from TEI source files.</p>
<p part="N">After careful consideration, we propose minor changes to the <gi scheme="TEI">event</gi> and <gi scheme="TEI">listEvent</gi>
            elements. To allow for multiple levels of reporting on events, we will discuss a nested
            and typed way of distinguishing between describing and described events.</p>
<p part="N">Merging data on historical events from various sources will provide for a closer linking
            of text editions. It will also provide data for an enriched historical background by
            linking events across editions. We hope to enable the TEI community to generalize what
            has lately been successfully adopted for correspondences under the correspSearch label –
            including a web service –, while staying in line with the generic norms and the specific
            needs that arise from other types of sources.</p>
</div>
</body>