<body>
<div>
<head>Authors</head>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">Daria Maximova</hi> (National Research University Higher School of
          Economics, Moscow, RU)</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">Frank Fischer</hi> (DARIAH-EU and National Research University Higher
          School of Economics, Moscow, RU)</p>
</div>
<div>
<head>Abstract</head>
<p>The <hi rend="italic">&lt;stage&gt;</hi> tag is a core element for the encoding of drama.
          The TEI guidelines suggest nine values for its <hi rend="italic">type</hi> attribute,
          which is widely used in large corpora such as the French <hi rend="italic">Théâtre
            Classique</hi>, the Shakespeare Folger Library or the Swedish <hi rend="italic">Dramawebben</hi>. This paper introduces an approach to automatically assign
          stage-direction types to the TEI-P5-encoded Russian Drama Corpus, RusDraCor
          (https://dracor.org/). The corpus currently features 144 plays ranging from mid-18th to        
  mid-20th century which makes for 32 753 stage directions with 144,525 tokens.</p>
<p>We selected 18 plays comprising 6,569 stage directions to represent the breadth of the
          corpus. For the manual annotation we established a clear set of rules to identify the
          stage-direction types proposed by the TEI guidelines
          (https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-stage.html).</p>
<p>Following the annotation of our subcorpus, we developed a tool for the classification of
          the remaining plays without human interference. For the conversion of stage directions
          into feature vectors, we used morphological and semantic data. Our tool in its current
          state is able to classify different types with an F1 score of approx. 0.75, which means
          that 3 out of 4 stage directions of any given type are assigned correctly.</p>
<p>Our work will inform a dedicated analysis of stage directions, which after preliminary
          studies by Sperantov (1998) and Detken (2009) will be based on larger corpora allowing for
          a description of the evolvement of stage directions over 200 years.</p>
</div>
</body>