<body>
<p>Underlying uncertainty in DH research data affects decision-making and persists during
            the project’s lifecycle. This uncertainty will always be present. Thus, efforts in
            providing technical support for humanistic research should focus on managing and making
            it more transparent, rather than removing it.</p>
<p>Locating and tracing (certain types of) uncertainty through the evolution of a textual
            corpus can be done with the use of TEI tags <ref target="#consortium19" type="bibl">[TEI
               Consortium 2019]</ref>. However, the use of these methods is not a common practice.
            The motivation of this paper is to address one possible barrier to wider use of these
            tags by providing a user-friendly interface to collaboratively annotating texts with
            uncertainty. We propose some minor extensions of the TEI specification that follow from
            our metrics of uncertainty. The first extension is adding the new <q>category</q>
            attribute to the <q>certainty</q> element, required to indicate the source of
            uncertainty. The second extension is to change the closed list of values of the
               <q>locus</q> attribute to an open list, in order to be able to explicitly indicate
            the attribute to which uncertainty refers.</p>
<p>Additionally, the authors detected a need to describe the nature and type of
            uncertainties as well as evaluating the degree of uncertainty the piece of data
            introduces <ref target="#theron19" type="bibl">[Therón et al. 2019]</ref>.</p>
<p>Our tools on the platform were developed against the background of human-centered design
            with the focus onto easing uncertainty annotation and visualization, promoting the use
            of TEI standards and making uncertainty play a more active role in the research
            process.</p>
<p>The platform fulfils the common needs of a complete research lifecycle by providing
            well-known technologies for basic tasks, such as versioning, file management, text
            editing, and reference resource management.</p>
<figure>
<graphic mimeType="image/png" url="info:fedora/o:tei2019.168" xml:id="IMAGE.1"/>
<desc>Screenshot of the collaborative TEI editor on the PROVIDEDH Open
               Science Platform</desc>
</figure>
<p>The authors aim to get feedback from the TEI community to improve their tools in a
            generic way and fulfill further needs of the audience.</p>
</body>