<body>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">Challenges in encoding parliamentary data: between applause and
                    interjections</hi>
</p>
<p>Parliamentary data has always been of great interest to researchers in the social
                sciences and the humanities. There are many initiatives at European and national
                levels for compiling digital collections of parliamentary data. However, these
                initiatives use different encoding schemes to present parliamentary data ranging
                from ad hoc ones, over specific standards for representing legislation (e.g. Akoma
                Ntoso) to TEI. Akoma Ntoso has been created to make the structural and semantic
                components of digital parliamentary documents fully accessible to machine-driven
                    processes<note n="1" place="foot" xml:id="ftn1">
<p rend="footnote text">
<ref target="https://unsceb-hlcm.github.io/part1/index-13.html">https://unsceb-hlcm.github.io/part1/index-13.html</ref> (accessed
                        11.05.2019)</p>
</note>. However, this encoding standard was not designed to
                include linguistic annotation. In this regards TEI is more suitable. The Austrian
                parliamentary record corpus, ParlAT (Wissik &amp; Pirker 2018), which was before
                only available in a vertical format suitable for analysis in a corpus query system,
                is now being encoded in TEI. In this contribution, we will present the encountered
                challenges, often related to the fact, that the Austrian parliamentary records are
                edited shorthand records of the parliamentary sessions and not transcripts of
                recordings. The Austrian parliamentary records include a lot of comments within
                parenthesis and formatted differently than the other text, namely in italics. These
                comments range from indicating applause or laughter to indicating interjections. We
                decided to encode these comments in different ways using the elements from the
                transcription of speech module: to use &lt;incident&gt; for comments indicating
                applause or laughter and &lt;u&gt; (utterance) for comments indicating
                    interjections<note n="2" place="foot" xml:id="ftn2">
<p rend="footnote text">
                        Parts of this research were supported by a CLARIN Mobility Grant allowing a
                        research visit at the Jožef Stefan Institute as part of CLARIN
                    Slovenia.</p>
</note>. In the contribution, we will discuss the solutions for
                encoding such comments, regarding the Austrian case but also in relation to a more
                general scheme proposed by Tomaž Erjavec and Andrej Pančur, the teiParla<note n="3" place="foot" xml:id="ftn3">
<p rend="footnote text">
                        https://www.clarin.eu/event/2019/parlaformat-workshop</p>
</note>.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">References</hi>
</p>
<p>
<hi rend="citeproc-contributors">Wissik, T. and Pirker, H.</hi> (<hi rend="citeproc-date">2018</hi>). <hi rend="citeproc-title">ParlAT beta Corpus of
                    Austrian Parliamentary Records</hi>. In: D. Fišer, M. Eskevich, F. de Jong, ed.,
                <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">LREC2018 Workshop ParlaCLARIN: Creating and Using Parliamentary Corpora </hi>In:
                    <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the Eleventh International Conference on
                    Language Resources and Evaluation LREC2018</hi>. <hi rend="citeproc-publisher-place">Miyazaki</hi>
<hi rend="citeproc-publisher">:
                    European Language Resources Association</hi>, 20-23.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">Keywords</hi>
</p>
<p>Parliamentary records, TEI, transcript of speech module, encoding applause, encoding
                interjections</p>
</body>