<body>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">correspSearch v2 – New ways of exploring
                    correspondence</hi>
</p>
<p>The webservice correspSearch has been developed since 2014 to aggregate
                correspondence metadata and offers it to the scientific community for research and
                retrieval. The data is obtained in the TEI-XML-based "Correspondence Metadata
                Interchange Format" (CMIF) - developed by the TEI Correspondence SIG. A prototype
                was presented at the TEI Conference in Lyon in 2015.</p>
<p>Since 2017, the web service has been further developed in a project funded by the
                German Research Foundation (DFG). At the same time, the data quantity increased from
                around 25,000 to over 52,000 letters - many editions offer letter metadata in CMIF
                by now. In order to enable even small edition projects to deliver data in CMIF and
                to simplify the capture of letter metadata from printed editions, the CMIF Creator
                was developed in 2018 to allow a convenient browser-based input and processing of
                metadata into CMIF.</p>
<p>Over time, the development of the web service focused on both, the system
                architecture and the improvement of the search, which now - in accordance with the
                ongoing development of CMIF - for the first time does capture letter content as
                well. In addition, several different editions of one letter can be linked to each
                other or connected to associated archives. To add on that, correspSearch does offer
                a map-based, geographical search for writing and receiving locations by now. The API
                interfaces and networking possibilities of correspSearch have also been extended.
                With csLink, a JavaScript-based widget to present correspondence networks is now
                available on GitHub as open source software that can be integrated into any digital
                edition.</p>
<p>The article will present and discuss the further development of the web service, as
                well as the community’s experiences with the aggregation of metadata. During the
                presentation, the second version of correspSearch will be released as public
                beta.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">Bibliography</hi>
</p>
<p>Dumont, Stefan: „correspSearch – Connecting Scholarly Editions of Letters“, Journal
                of the Text Encoding Initiative Issue 10 (2016), <ref target="http://journals.openedition.org/jtei/1742">
<hi rend="underline color(1155cc)">http://journals.openedition.org/jtei/1742</hi>
</ref>
</p>
<p>TEI Correspondence SIG (Hrsg.): „Correspondence Metadata Interchange Format (CMIF)“,
                2018.2015, <ref target="https://github.com/TEI-Correspondence-SIG/CMIF">
<hi rend="underline color(1155cc)">https://github.com/TEI-Correspondence-SIG/CMIF</hi>
</ref>
</p>
</body>