<body>
<p rend="center">Inscriptions, Hieroglyphs, Linguistics... and Beyond! The Corpus of
                Classic Mayan as an Ontological Information Resource</p>
<p rend="center">Franziska Diehr, Sven Gronemeyer, Uwe Sikora, Christian Prager,
                Maximilian Brodhun, Elisabeth Wagner, Katja Diederichs, Nikolai Grube</p>
<p rend="justify">Answering the question “What is text, really?” may be impossible, for
                ‘text’ being a most complex resource, fulfilling numerous purposes, manifested in
                diverse documents types with unique characteristics. To study ‘text’ using digital
                methods, some kind of representation is required. The project ‘Text Database and          
      Dictionary of Classic Mayan’<hi rend="sup">
<note n="1" place="foot" xml:id="ftn1">
<hi rend="sup"/>For more information on the project, see: <ptr target="http://mayadictionary.de/"/>
</note>
</hi> compiles the hieroglyphic texts written by the ancient Maya in a
                machine-readable corpus. We do so with an approach fitting the idea of “TEI and
                beyond”: ‘Text’ is represented as separate information resources, each described by
                an ontological model representing the specific semantics and complexities of the
                material. Using different formats (RDF, XML) and standards (CIDOC-CRM, TEI-P5), the
                inscriptions are encoded in a multi-level corpus:<hi rend="sup">
<note n="2" place="foot" xml:id="ftn2">
<hi rend="sup"/>The corpus further consists of (4)
                        an ontological-based RDF-schema for historical and scholarly information and
                        physical features of text carriers, and (5) the ‘Maya Image Archive’ for
                        photographic and archival material, for which we use the DARIAH service
                        ‘ConedaKOR’: <ptr target="https://classicmayan.kor.de.dariah.eu/"/>.
                    </note>
</hi> (1) a TEI-all conform schema defining values and rules for the
                encoding of the text’s topological and structural features, (2) a ‘Sign Catalogue’
                for the classification of Maya hieroglyphs (Diehr et al.), and (3) the tool ‘ALMAH’
                for linguistic analyses (Grube et. al, 5-7).</p>
<p rend="justify">Maya writing is not yet fully deciphered, not all signs are known, and
                we still deal with competing reading hypotheses and a missing Unicode character
                    set.<hi rend="sup">
<note n="3" place="foot" xml:id="ftn3"> There are efforts in
                        this direction (Pallan Gayol, Anderson), but in their current form they do
                        not meet the classification requirements of the Maya script. These
                        challenges are also present in other ancient, non-alphabetic writing systems
                        (Rossi, De Santis). The interdisciplinary working group EnCoWS (Encoding
                        Complex Writing Systems) was set up in 2015 for the purpose of harmonising
                        encodings.</note>
</hi> To represent the script, we use stand-off markup to
                enable an interlinked structure between distributed sources: The TEI encoding serves
                as central data source, embedding other information (Fig. 1). Maya glyphs are
                grouped in blocks, each usually containing more than one in different
                    arrangements.<hi rend="sup">
<note n="4" place="foot" xml:id="ftn4">
<p> Depending
                            on space requirements and aesthetics, individual signs merge, overlap,
                            be</p>
<p rend="justify">infixed, or rotated, depending on the sign shape
                            and space within the block.</p>
</note>
</hi>
</p>
<p rend="justify">Using @rend and @corresp represents this structure by describing the
                position to the neighboring glyph.<hi rend="sup">
<note n="5" place="foot" xml:id="ftn5">
<p> By using @corresp to refer to the neighboring glyph, we mimic a
                            numerical transliteration</p>
<p rend="justify">(similar to the ‘Leiden
                            Conventions’), but in a more precise way: With support of the</p>
<p rend="justify">TEI semantics and the XML syntax an unambiguous
                            description of the glyph arrangement</p>
<p rend="justify">is
                            provided.</p>
</note>
</hi> The project will encode approximately 10,000
                    texts.<hi rend="sup">
<note n="6" place="foot" xml:id="ftn6">
<p> The data will
                            successively be made accessible under a CC BY-4.0 license on our
                            project</p>
<p rend="justify">portal (https://www.classicmayan.org/)
                            which is currently in the stage of conception.</p>
<p rend="justify">Furthermore, the corpus data will also be published in the TextGrid
                            Repository (https:</p>
<p rend="justify">//textgridrep.org/), where they
                            can also be accessed by external users via OAI-PMH.</p>
<p rend="justify">The RDF data of the Sign Catalogue will be also retrievable at the
                            portal via a SPARQL</p>
<p rend="justify">endpoint and also at the TG
                            Rep.</p>
</note>
</hi> To support the workflow, we developed a parser that
                creates the according TEI/XML structure out of a project-specific sign number
                transliteration (Grube et. al, 2-3).</p>
<p rend="justify">In our approach, ‘text’ is understood as a multi-level information
                resource in form of an ontological corpus, offering different views and access
                points to the material, providing a holistic environment for studying Classic
                Mayan.</p>
<p rend="justify">
<figure>
<graphic mimeType="image/png" url="info:fedora/o:tei2019.139" xml:id="IMAGE.1"/>
<desc type="legend">Figure 1: Within tei:g the value of attribute @ref refers to the URI ofthe
                        graph recorded in the Sign Catalogue. Its ontological structure links
                        thegraph to its linguistic expression, to which a transliteration value is
                        assigned.</desc>
</figure>
</p>
<p rend="justify">References</p>
<p rend="justify">Franziska Diehr, Sven Gronemeyer, Elisabeth Wagner, Christian Prager,
                Katja Diederichs, Uwe Sikora, Maximilian Brodhun, and Nikolai Grube. Modelling
                vagueness: A criteria-based system for the qualitative assessment of reading
                proposals for the deciphering of Classic Mayan hieroglyphs.In Michael Piotrowski,
                editor, Proceedings of the Workshop on Computational Methods in the Humanities 2018,
                volume 2314 of Workshop Proceedings, pages 33–44, Lausanne, Switzerland, 2019.
                CEUR.</p>
<p rend="justify">Nikolai Grube, Christian Prager, Katja Diederichs, Sven Gronemeyer,
                Antje Grothe, Céline Tamignaux, Elisabeth Wagner, Maximilian Brodhun, and Franziska
                Diehr. Textdatenbank und Wörterbuch des Klassischen Maya Annual Report for 2017.
                Textdatenbank und Wörterbuch des Klassischen Maya, (Project Report 5), 2018.</p>
<p rend="justify">Carlos Pallan Gayol and Deborah Anderson. Achieving Machine-Readable
                Mayan Text via Unicode: Blending “Old World” Script-encoding with Novel Digital
                Approaches. In Élika Ortega, Glen Worthey, Isabel Galina, and Ernesto Priani,
                editors, Digital Humanities 2018 - Puentes-Bridges: Book of Abstracts, pages
                256–261, Mexico City.</p>
<p rend="justify">Irene Rossi and Annamaria De Santis. Crossing Experiences in Digital
                Epigraphy: From Practice to Discipline. De Gruyter, Berlin, 2019.</p>
</body>