<body>
<p>Making Linkable Data from Account Books: Bookkeeping Ontology in the Digital Edition
                Publishing Cooperative for Historical Accounts</p>
<p>Christopher Pollin and Kathryn Tomasek</p>
<p>TEI2019, University of Graz</p>
<p>Historical accounting records, a genre of manuscript document that can be encoded in
                TEI/XML, can be a rich source about local social and economic relationships in the
                past as well for comparative purposes. With the Digital Edition Publication
                Cooperative for Historical Accounts (DEPCHA), documentary editors and developers in
                the United States collaborated with digital humanists at the Zentrum für
                Informationsmodellierung (Centre for Information Modeling) at the University of Graz
                to apply a bookkeeping ontology to accounts.</p>
<p>The main use cases for this project are the Financial Papers of George Washington
                (Stertzer), accounting records from a store on the Stagville Plantation in North
                Carolina (Brumfield and Agbe-Davies), and a day book kept by Laban Morey Wheaton, a
                businessman who kept a dry goods store in Norton, Massachusetts, between 1828 and
                1859 (Tomasek and Bauman).</p>
<p>This paper focuses on a workflow for creating linkable data using the TEI <hi style="font-family:Courier">@ana</hi> attribute. While the Wheaton edition was
                created using TEI-XML, the data for the Washington Financial Papers and for the
                Stagville store were created using Drupal and FromthePage, respectively.
                Transformation to TEI-XML for these records is an interim step for creating the RDF
                for linking on the Web of Data (Pollin 2019). Examples will be drawn from the
                Stagville/FromthePage and Wheaton/TEI-XML data. Upcoming work on building a bridge
                from Drupal to TEI-XML is part of the project’s ongoing research agenda.</p>
<p>Part of the workflow for creating RDF includes use of WikiData and OpenRefine. Since
                the currency, goods, and services exchanged had contextual meanings grounded in both
                place and time, ongoing work also focuses on mapping information from taxonomies
                based on the digital editions of the primary sources to Historical Statistics of the
                United States, a long-standing project in U.S. economic history. Examples will
                include an alpha-version TEI taxonomy drawn from this source. Future work will
                involve mapping taxonomies from the Washington Financial Papers onto this TEI
                taxonomy and expanding it accordingly.</p>
<p>References</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Bicentennial Edition: Historical Statistics of the United States,
                    Colonial Times to 1970</hi>. <ref target="https://www.census.gov/library/publications/1975/compendia/hist_stats_colonial-1970.html">https://www.census.gov/library/publications/1975/compendia/hist_stats_colonial-1970.html</ref>
</p>
<p>Brumfield, Ben, and Anna Agbe-Davies. Encoding Account Books Relating to Slavery in
                the U.S. South. 2015. <ref target="https://medea.hypotheses.org/182">
<hi rend="Internetverknüpfung">https://medea.hypotheses.org/182</hi>
</ref>
</p>
<p>DEPCHA prototype: <ref target="https://gams.uni-graz.at/depcha">
<hi rend="ListLabel_2">https://gams.uni-graz.at/depcha</hi>
</ref>
</p>
<p>Historical Statistics of the United States. Millenial Edition Online. <ref target="https://hsus.cambridge.org/HSUSWeb/toc/hsusHome.do">
<hi rend="Internetverknüpfung">https://hsus.cambridge.org/HSUSWeb/toc/hsusHome.do</hi>
</ref>
</p>
<p>Pollin, Christopher. <ref target="https://chpollin.github.io/paper/RODBH_2019_paper_1.pdf">
<hi rend="Internetverknüpfung">Digital Edition Publishing Cooperative for
                        Historical Accounts and the Bookkeeping Ontology</hi>
</ref>. forthcoming
                2019. </p>
<p>Stertzer, Jennifer. Working with the Financial Records of George Washington: Document
                vs. Data. Digital Studies/Le champ
                numérique<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">. </hi>2014. DOI: <ref target="http://doi.org/10.16995/dscn.57">
<hi rend="ListLabel_3">http://doi.org/10.16995/dscn.57</hi>
</ref>
</p>
<p>Tomasek, Kathryn, and Syd Bauman. Encoding Financial Records for Historical Research.
                Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative. 6. 2013. <ref target="https://journals.openedition.org/jtei/895">https://journals.openedition.org/jtei/895</ref>
</p>
</body>