<body>
<p>
<hi rend="bold" style="font-size:11pt">TEI 2019 Abstract</hi>
</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold" style="font-size:11pt">Suggestions for Refining the Current Teaching
                    Methodology of the TEI through the Analysis of Server Logs</hi>
</p>
<p>
<hi style="font-size:11pt">Luis Meneses, Electronic Textual Cultures Lab, University
                    of Victoria, ldmm@uvic.ca</hi>
</p>
<p>
<hi style="font-size:11pt">Jonathan Martin, King’s College London,
                    jonathan.d.martin@kcl.ac.uk Luis Meneses and Jonathan Martin</hi>
</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold" style="font-size:11pt">Keywords:</hi>
<hi style="font-size:11pt">server logs, teaching methodology, TEI
                Guidelines</hi>
</p>
<p>
<hi style="font-size:11pt">Great emphasis has been placed lately on the pedagogy and
                    practice of the TEI Guidelines [1]. In teaching and learning the TEI Guidelines
                    we engage scholars in real research partnerships: allowing them to produce
                    digital editions for their own studies and explore different aspects of their
                    texts through different perspectives.</hi>
</p>
<p>
<hi style="font-size:11pt">We believe that the next step in the evolution of the TEI
                    is developing training materials, which aligns with Greatthe emphasis that has
                    been placed lately on the pedagogy and practice of the TEI Guidelines –which was
                    the main theme of the 2017 conference (“TEI Victoria 2017” 2019)[1].. The
                    materials for learning the TEI Guidelines are still in early stages –consisting
                    primarily of past project documentation, the TEI’s own introductory materials,
                    online tutorials, and collected examples –</hi>
<hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve">which leads to skills being acquired in unsystematic ways </hi>
<hi style="font-size:11pt">. Additionally, the Guidelines have evolved and become
                    more rigorous and theoretical –making some of these training materials
                    overwhelming and unpractical for newcomers who might not be familiar with text
                    encoding. As proponents of the TEI Guidelines, In teaching and learning the TEI
                    Guidelines we engage scholars in real research partnerships: allowing them to
                    produce digital editions for their own studies and explore different aspects of
                    their texts through different perspectives.As the Guidelines have matured and
                    become more rigorous and theoretical,</hi>
<hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve">we have an disciplinary obligation to develop equally rigorous adequate and standardized appropriate training materials for new learners. </hi>
</p>
<p>
<hi style="font-size:11pt">The current TEI Infrastructure consists of a set of
                    servers and services</hi>
<hi style="font-size:11pt">, allowing the Guidelines to be primarily accessed
                    online. A server log is a file automatically created and maintained by a server
                    consisting of a list of activities it performed. For our purposes, a statistical
                    analysis of server logs can be used to examine Web traffic patterns. In this
                    abstract, we propose to analyze the TEI server logs in order to propose offer
                    suggestions to refine the teaching methodology based on what parts of the
                    Guidelines are more frequently accessed –while also considering what is not
                    accessed often. Additionally, we are aware that</hi>
<hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve">customizations of the Guidelines exist that aim to meet the majority of the needs of TEI user community –(for example, TEI Lite </hi>
<hi style="font-size:11pt">). However, formal justifications for which elements are
                    included and excluded in them do not exist. This proposal interrogates and
                    theorizes how we might present the TEI Guidelines as better teaching materials
                    and aims to foster the development of skills and activities of future
                    scholars.</hi>
</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold" style="font-size:11pt">References</hi>
</p>
<p rend="Bibliography">
<hi style="font-size:11pt">Cayless, Hugh, James Cummings, Martin Holmes, Peter
                    Stadler, and Magdalena Turska. 2018. “TEI Technical Infrastructure.” presented
                    at the TEI 2018: 18th annual Conference and Members Meeting of the Text Encoding
                    Initiative Consortium, Tokyo, Japan, September 9.</hi>
</p>
<p rend="Bibliography">
<hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve">Jakacki, Diane. 2016. “How We Teach? Digital Humanities Pedagogy in an Imperfect World.” </hi>
<hi rend="italic" style="font-size:11pt">Diane Jakacki</hi>
<hi style="font-size:11pt">. June 5.
                    http://dianejakacki.net/how-we-teach-digital-humanities-pedagogy-in-an-imperfect-world/.</hi>
</p>
<p rend="Bibliography">
<hi style="font-size:11pt">“TEI Lite – TEI: Text Encoding
                    Initiative.” 2019. Accessed April 22.
                    https://tei-c.org/guidelines/customization/lite/.</hi>
</p>
<p rend="Bibliography">
<hi style="font-size:11pt">“TEI Victoria 2017.” 2019. Accessed
                    April 22. https://hcmc.uvic.ca/tei2017/.</hi>
</p>
<p rend="Bibliography">
<hi style="font-size:11pt">[1] “TEI Victoria 2017.” [Online].
                    Available: https://hcmc.uvic.ca/tei2017/. [Accessed: 22-Apr-2019].</hi>
</p>
<p rend="Bibliography">
<hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve">[2]	D. Jakacki, “How we Teach? Digital Humanities Pedagogy in an Imperfect World,” </hi>
<hi rend="italic" style="font-size:11pt">Diane Jakacki</hi>
<hi style="font-size:11pt">, 05-Jun-2016. [Online]. Available:
                    http://dianejakacki.net/how-we-teach-digital-humanities-pedagogy-in-an-imperfect-world/.
                    [Accessed: 22-Apr-2019].</hi>
</p>
<p rend="Bibliography">
<hi style="font-size:11pt">[3] H. Cayless, J. Cummings, M.
                    Holmes, P. Stadler, and M. Turska, “TEI Technical Infrastructure,” presented at
                    the TEI 2018: 18th annual Conference and Members Meeting of the Text Encoding
                    Initiative Consortium, Tokyo, Japan, 09-Sep-2018.</hi>
</p>
<p rend="Bibliography">
<hi style="font-size:11pt">[4] “TEI Lite – TEI: Text Encoding
                    Initiative.” [Online]. Available:
                    https://tei-c.org/guidelines/customization/lite/. [Accessed:
                22-Apr-2019].</hi>
</p>
</body>