<body>
<div>
<p rend="Title">Text Graph Ontology </p>
<p rend="Subtitle">A Semantic Web approach to represent genetic scholarly
                    editions</p>
<p>Peter Hinkelmanns, University of Salzburg</p>
<p>A model of text as a variant graph can support representing genetic text
                    editions. The proposed model makes it possible to describe the relations between
                    tokens and their relative dependencies in text genesis. The main focus is on the
                    representation of intradocumentary text revisions. Moreover the
                    Text-Graph-Ontology enables the referencing of genetic text editions via the <hi rend="italic">Semantic Web</hi>. In addition to this ontology, a converter
                    from and to TEI-XML and a web-based viewer and editor will be presented.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Graph, Ontology, Semantic Web, Genetic Text Editions</hi>
</p>
<p>Text genetic editions are enjoying sustained popularity in the fields of
                    scholarly editions and literary studies. Representatives of recent research
                    projects are the Faust edition (Bohnenkamp, Henke, and Jannidis 2016) or the
                    edition of the works of Arthur Schnitzler (Burch et al. 2016), both of which aim
                    at a complete reproduction of the text genesis. These editions require the
                    reconstruction of complex text genetic processes. Which sequence of tokens forms
                    a specific text state? How can differences between versions be described? The
                    extension of the model of the Text Encoding Initiative by elements required for
                    genetic editions was the subject of a working group that presented its results
                    in a draft (Burnard et al. 2010). Parts of this draft have been incorporated
                    into the TEI Guidelines (TEI Consortium 2013). With TEI P5, complex genetic
                    editions can be realized. However, the underlying structure of the hierarchical
                    graph makes it difficult to reconstruct and compare text gradients, i.e. the
                    evolutionary stages of a text with inline markup. It can of course be done using
                    stand-off and out-of-line annotations, as James Cummings has pointed out
                    (Cummings 2018, 13). This concept for a Text Graph Ontology does not aim to be
                    the next paper criticizing the xml foundation of TEI P5 nor is it trying to
                    compete with the interoperability of TEI encoded texts. The ontology is designed
                    for the specific purpose of implementing a text variant graph using semantic web
                    technologies for the encoding of genetic text editions.</p>
</div>
<div>
<head>Data models for textual representation</head>
<p>Several project used graphs to represent textual variation in the recent years.
                    They can be divided into methods based on markup and methods focusing on variant
                    graphs. An approach to deal with the problem of overlapping annotations in XML
                    is the proposed markup language ‘General Ordered-Descendant Directed Acyclic
                    Graph’ (GODDAG: Sperberg-McQueen and Huitfeldt 2004, esp. 158). A similar model
                    is the ‘Graph Annotation Format’ (GrAF: Ide and Suderman 2007) which extends the
                    Linguistic Annotation Framework (LAF: Ide and Romary 2006). In GRaF an
                    underlying text is segmented via stand-off nodes, which use the position of
                    characters in the text as reference points. Edges link the annotations with text
                    segments. </p>
<p>The problem of intradocumentary and intertextual variation is addressed by the
                    ‘data structure for representing multi-version texts’ (Schmidt and Colomb 2009).
                    Thy criticize the markup approach of models like GODDAG and GrAF (Schmidt and
                    Colomb 2009, 499) and propose a variant graph where the edges contain the
                    segments of texts shared by multiple variants:</p>
<figure>
<graphic mimeType="image/png" url="info:fedora/o:tei2019.172" xml:id="IMAGE.1"/>
<desc type="legend">Fig. 1:<hi rend="normalweight" xml:space="preserve"> A variant graph (Figure by Schmidt and Colomb 2009, 502)</hi>
</desc>
</figure>
<p>The sigils indicate the different variants of the text between different text
                    carriers. Individual tokens of a specific text carrier are not represented.</p>
<p>Collating texts is the focus of the stemmaweb project (“The Stemmaweb Project”
                    2012–; Andrews and Mace 2013). Similar to Schmidt and Colomb 2009 a variation
                    graph is used to represent versions of a text. The texts are segmented into
                    tokens and form the nodes of the graph. Directed edges show the similarities and
                    dissimilarities between individual text carriers. Undirected edges represent
                    variant relationships like orthographic variation, grammatical variation,
                    lexical variation etc. (Andrews and Mace 2013, 508).</p>
<figure>
<graphic mimeType="image/png" url="info:fedora/o:tei2019.172" xml:id="IMAGE.2"/>
<desc type="legend">Fig. 2: <hi rend="normalweight">Screenshot of the ‘Text relationship
                            mapper’ of Stemmaweb, showing an extract of Segment 1 of the Chronicle
                            of Matthew (Figure by “The Stemmaweb Project” 2012–)</hi>
</desc>
</figure>
<p>Efer 2016 has comprehensively described the use of graph databases for the
                    text-oriented Digital Humanities. He proposed ‘Kadmos’, a layered graph model
                    for textual representation. His model includes the separation into types and
                    tokens:</p>
<figure>
<graphic mimeType="image/png" url="info:fedora/o:tei2019.172" xml:id="IMAGE.3"/>
<desc type="legend">Fig. 3: <hi rend="normalweight">Schematic representation of instance data
                            sets and links of a short example document with minimalistic text data
                            model (Figure by Efer 2016, 76)</hi>
</desc>
</figure>
<p>The ‘Text as Graph’ model (TAG: Haentjens Dekker and Birnbaum 2017) stores the
                    text in nodes of various length (Haentjens Dekker and Birnbaum 2017, §3). A
                    token may be split into several nodes and marked up as a word:</p>
<figure>
<graphic mimeType="image/png" url="info:fedora/o:tei2019.172" xml:id="IMAGE.4"/>
<desc type="legend">Fig. 4: <hi rend="normalweight">A simplified poem with word tokenization
                            (Figure by Haentjens Dekker and Birnbaum 2017, Fig. 10)</hi>
</desc>
</figure>
<p>TAG is at the current stage defined as a data model and not as a syntactic
                    representation (Haentjens Dekker and Birnbaum 2017, §2.1).</p>
<p>This very brief overview of selected data models for textual representation has
                    shown, that multiple models for the representation of texts as graphs exist. The
                    proposed model of this paper is far from state of a stable model and aims to
                    connect the idea of a variation graph with semantic web technologies.</p>
</div>
<div>
<head>Text graph ontology</head>
<p>The Semantic Web makes information accessible in a machine-readable way using
                    standardized vocabularies and ontologies. A distinction is made between ‘nodes’,
                    which can be objects or atomic values, and ‘edges’, which describe the
                    relationship between nodes. A statement always consists of a triple ‘[subject] -
                    [predicate] - [object]’. Semantic Web technologies enable easy annotating and
                    linking the scholarly genetic edition other resources. The Text Graph Ontology
                    uses the Web Ontology Language (OWL: W3C OWL Working Group 2012) to specify
                    classes and properties. </p>
<p>The first problem which needs to be addressed is the segmentation of a text.
                    There is no agreement between the briefly presented models on what the atomic
                    unit of a text graph is. For the Text Graph Ontology tokens separated by white
                    space should be assumed, with the possibility to extend the model on a sub token
                    level. A diplomatic transcription and various normalization stages can be
                    attached to a token as a string or generatet from a separated character
                    graph.</p>
<p>The proposals for the annotation of text revisions of the Grazer Editionsphilogie
                    are tailored to the needs of mediaeval editions. Hofmeister-Winter 2016 presents
                    a categorization of text revision phenomena. She distinguishes between
                    self-revisions, i.e. interventions in one's own text, and external revisions,
                    which describe the interventions of another hand (Hofmeister-Winter 2016, 10).
                    Self-revisions can be a direct component of text production (immediate revision)
                    or take place at a later point in time (late revision). In their opinion,
                    third-party revisions, on the other hand, take place exclusively in a later
                    revision step as a late revision. Furthermore, the following typology is
                    established by the Graz project (Hofmeister, Böhm, and Klug 2016, 22):</p>
<list type="ordered">
<item>
<hi rend="bold">eradication</hi> by bleaching, deletion, blackening,
                        expansion</item>
<item>
<hi rend="bold">transformation</hi> resp. transformation by overwriting,
                        addition, reduction</item>
<item>
<hi rend="bold">insertion</hi> in all described positions (interlinear,
                        linear, marginal) after eradication by deletion or bleaching, with
                        instruction signs in different shapes, single or paired, as well as gap
                        filling after precautionary recess</item>
</list>
<p>To represent these revisions, an edge weighted directed acyclic graph is used.
                    The limitations of RDF make is necessary to construct weighted edges as
                    individual nodes. The base model therefore consists of three node classes:
                    Tokens, Connectors and Borders (the empty start and end nodes of a graph):</p>
<figure>
<graphic mimeType="image/png" url="info:fedora/o:tei2019.172" xml:id="IMAGE.5"/>
<desc>Fig. 5: <hi rend="normalweight">‚Hello World‘ as a weighted text graph in
                            RDF</hi>
</desc>
</figure>
<p>The weight represents the relative order of edges from one token to the next. A
                    substitution would therefore be represented as follows:</p>
<figure>
<graphic mimeType="image/png" url="info:fedora/o:tei2019.172" xml:id="IMAGE.6"/>
<desc>Fig. 6: <hi rend="normalweight">‚Hello</hi>
<hi rend="normalweight strikethrough">World</hi>
<hi rend="normalweight" xml:space="preserve"> Graz‘ as a weighted text graph in RDF</hi>
</desc>
</figure>
<p>The path following the lowest weight is the first, the past following the highest
                    weight is the last version of the text. The reconstruction of a particular text
                    state can be described as a path through the text. Deletions and additions of
                    text can be seen in the graph accordingly:</p>
<figure>
<graphic mimeType="image/png" url="info:fedora/o:tei2019.172" xml:id="IMAGE.7"/>
<desc>Fig. 7: <hi rend="normalweight">Transformation, addition and deletion in a
                            weighted text graph</hi>
</desc>
</figure>
<p>A conversion of this small graph to TEI P5 is possible:</p>
<p rend="code">&lt;del&gt;Hello&lt;/del&gt;
                    &lt;subst&gt;&lt;del&gt;World&lt;/del&gt;&lt;add&gt;Graz&lt;/add&gt;&lt;/subst&gt;
                    &lt;add&gt;TEI&lt;/add&gt;</p>
<p>To mark specific stages of a text, the Connectors are being referenced to a text
                    stage:</p>
<figure>
<graphic mimeType="image/png" url="info:fedora/o:tei2019.172" xml:id="IMAGE.8"/>
<desc>Fig. 8: <hi rend="normalweight">Text stages realised in a variant text
                            graph</hi>
</desc>
</figure>
<p>The same variant graph method can be used to describe a token further on
                    character level:</p>
<figure>
<graphic mimeType="image/png" url="info:fedora/o:tei2019.172" xml:id="IMAGE.9"/>
<desc>Fig. 9: <hi rend="normalweight">Graph on character level</hi>
</desc>
</figure>
<p>This short article shows that semantic web technologies are suitable for
                    representing text variant graphs. The main benefit from using RDF is the
                    interconnectivity with other semantic web ressources. I. e. different text
                    carries of one text could be transcribed by different projects and easily be
                    linked with each other. Annotations on a text can directly point to authority
                    files and vice versa. Tools based on the model are a converter to and from TEI
                    P5 and a viewer/editor based on FLASK. The ontology and the tools will be
                    published on Github. A challenge of this graph approach that has not yet been
                    solved is rule-based validation.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Peter Hinkelmanns, Senior Scientist, University of Salzburg: Middle High German Conceptual Database, </hi>
<ref target="mailto:peter.hinkelmanns@sbg.ac.at">
<hi rend="italic">peter.hinkelmanns@sbg.ac.at</hi>
</ref>
</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Peter Hinkelmanns is a senior scientist at the Middle High
                        German Conceptual Database of the University of Salzburg. His research
                        interests include Middle High German lexicography, graph technologies in the
                        digital humanities and historic linguistics.</hi>
</p>
<p rend="Citavi Bibliography Heading">References</p>
<p rend="Citavi Bibliography Entry">
<anchor xml:id="CTVL001931a5a3feb7a4315939227c532263c64"/>Andrews, T. L., and C.
                    Mace. 2013. “Beyond the Tree of Texts: Building an Empirical Model of Scribal
                    Variation Through Graph Analysis of Texts and Stemmata.” <hi rend="italic">International Journal of Human-Computer Studies</hi> 28 (4): 504–21.
                    doi:10.1093/llc/fqt032.</p>
<p rend="Citavi Bibliography Entry">
<anchor xml:id="CTVL00191c11318f1554685b992de76ac73ad93"/>Bohnenkamp, Anne, Silke
                    Henke, and Fotis Jannidis. 2016. “Johann Wolfgang Goethe: Faust:
                    Historisch-Kritische Edition.” 2. Beta-Version. Accessed April 26, 2017. <ref target="http://beta.faustedition.net/">http://beta.faustedition.net/</ref>.</p>
<p rend="Citavi Bibliography Entry">
<anchor xml:id="CTVL0019e9e4a3322ae44dea64009a6141ad7aa"/>Burch, Thomas, Stefan
                    Büdenbender, Kristina Fink, Vivien Friedrich, Patrick Heck, Wolfgang Lukas,
                    Kathrin Nühlen et al. 2016. “Text[ge]schichten: Herausforderungen
                    Textgenetischen Edierens Bei Arthur Schnitzler.” In <hi rend="italic">Textgenese
                        Und Digitales Edieren: Wolfgang Koeppens „Jugend“ Im Kontext Der
                        Editionsphilologie</hi>, edited by Katharina Krüger, 87–105. Editio /
                    Beihefte, 40. Berlin, Boston: de Gruyter.</p>
<p rend="Citavi Bibliography Entry">
<anchor xml:id="CTVL00197181d2fb4344164969312c32399fca0"/>Burnard, Lou, Fotis
                    Jannidis, Elena Pierazzo, and Malte Rehbein. 2010. “An Encoding Model for
                    Genetic Editions.” Accessed March 25, 2019. <ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/Activities/Council/Working/tcw19.html">http://www.tei-c.org/Activities/Council/Working/tcw19.html</ref>.</p>
<p rend="Citavi Bibliography Entry">
<anchor xml:id="CTVL001d0e4342cf01c41cc97513885650ac382"/>Cummings, James. 2018. “A
                    World of Difference: Myths and Misconceptions About the TEI.” <hi rend="italic">Digital Scholarship Humanities</hi> 6:i63. doi:10.1093/llc/fqy071.</p>
<p rend="Citavi Bibliography Entry">
<anchor xml:id="CTVL001bafb080d815448eb91785c55de01ec3a"/>Efer, Thomas. 2016.
                    “Graphdatenbanken Für Die Textorientierten E-Humanities.” Dissertation,
                    Universität Leipzig.</p>
<p rend="Citavi Bibliography Entry">
<anchor xml:id="CTVL0014ab30991246c4d9a8b9c9e130c7916b0"/>Haentjens Dekker, Ronald,
                    and David J. Birnbaum. 2017. “It’s More Than Just Overlap: Text as Graph.” In
                        <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup Conference 2017</hi>,
                    edited by B. T. Usdin, Deborah A. Lapeyre, James D. Mason, C. M.
                    Sperberg-McQueen, and Norman Walsh. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies:
                    Mulberry Technologies, Inc.Rockville, Maryland.</p>
<p rend="Citavi Bibliography Entry">
<anchor xml:id="CTVL0014f0200bdb5e94bd6bd6ec5f67e0b7cad"/>Hofmeister, Wernfried,
                    Astrid Böhm, and Helmut W. Klug. 2016. “Die Deutschsprachigen Marginaltexte Der
                    Grazer Handschrift UB, Ms. 781 Als Interdisziplinärer Prüfstein Explorativer
                    Revisionsforschung Und Editionstechnik.” <hi rend="italic">Editio</hi> 30 (1):
                    14–33. doi:10.1515/editio-2016-0002.</p>
<p rend="Citavi Bibliography Entry">
<anchor xml:id="CTVL0017ecfa23b490046aaaed52762d36ff6d7"/>Hofmeister-Winter, Andrea.
                    2016. “Beredte Verbesserungen.” <hi rend="italic">Editio</hi> 30 (1): 1–13.
                    doi:10.1515/editio-2016-0001.</p>
<p rend="Citavi Bibliography Entry">
<anchor xml:id="CTVL001688920069d634898b9d6d5181b149cdd"/>Ide, Nancy, and Laurent
                    Romary. 2006. “Representing Linguistic Corpora and Their Annotations.” In <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the Fifth Language Resources and Evaluation
                        Conference: LREC 2006</hi>, edited by Nicoletta Calzolari, Khalid Choukri,
                    Aldo Gangemi, Bente Maegaard, Joseph Mariani, Jan Odijk, and Daniel Tapias:
                    Genua.</p>
<p rend="Citavi Bibliography Entry">
<anchor xml:id="CTVL001337749878b024a83b40b1a8d387d556f"/>Ide, Nancy, and Keith
                    Suderman. 2007. “GrAF: A Graph-Based Format for Linguistic Annotations.” In <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the Linguistic Annotation Workshop: Held in
                        Conjunction with ACL 2007</hi>, edited by Association for Computational
                    Linguistics, 1–8. <ref target="https://www.aclweb.org/anthology/W07-1501">https://www.aclweb.org/anthology/W07-1501</ref>. Accessed July 30,
                    2019.</p>
<p rend="Citavi Bibliography Entry">
<anchor xml:id="CTVL00138adb1eb8cd94504a45698d626c570fa"/>Schmidt, Desmond, and
                    Robert Colomb. 2009. “A Data Structure for Representing Multi-Version Texts
                    Online.” <hi rend="italic">International Journal of Human-Computer Studies</hi>
                    67 (6): 497–514. doi:10.1016/j.ijhcs.2009.02.001.</p>
<p rend="Citavi Bibliography Entry">
<anchor xml:id="CTVL001c5b6f773bc2c4b678f705c57545448f6"/>Sperberg-McQueen, C. M.,
                    and Claus Huitfeldt. 2004. “GODDAG: A Data Structure for Overlapping
                    Hierarchies.” In <hi rend="italic">Digital Documents: Systems and
                        Principles</hi>, edited by Peter King and Ethan V. Munson, 139–60. Berlin,
                    Heidelberg: Springer.</p>
<p rend="Citavi Bibliography Entry">
<anchor xml:id="CTVL0018c0b020bd5ec435b9c480e474de4d41d"/>TEI Consortium. 2013. “TEI
                    P5: Guidelines for Electronic Text Encoding and Interchange.” Version 3.6.0.
                    Accessed July 30, 2019. <ref target="https://www.tei-c.org/Vault/P5/3.6.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/">https://www.tei-c.org/Vault/P5/3.6.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/</ref>.</p>
<p rend="Citavi Bibliography Entry">
<anchor xml:id="CTVL001711889d72897449b9f0c1ff0e41f7e1c"/>“The Stemmaweb Project:
                    Tools and Techniques for Empirical Stemmatology.” 2012–. Accessed July 30, 2019.
                        <ref target="https://stemmaweb.net/">https://stemmaweb.net/</ref>.</p>
<p rend="Citavi Bibliography Entry">
<anchor xml:id="CTVL001a078baded4f44190ba66626659b5e6ce"/>W3C OWL Working Group.
                    2012. “OWL 2 Web Ontology Language: Document Overview (Second Edition).” W3C
                    Recommendation 11 December 2012. Accessed June 08, 2018. <ref target="https://www.w3.org/TR/owl2-overview/">https://www.w3.org/TR/owl2-overview/</ref>.</p>
</div>
</body>