<body>
<p>What we consider to be a line, how we count and number them, and how we encode them
               so that they can be analyzed and counted are deeply significant and yet fraught
               decisions. Lines numbers are a key critical metric in Early Modern Drama. Lines are
               the dominant measure of play and role length. Major critical arguments depend on
               whether and how much a character speaks in verse or prose; at the same time,
               editorial relineation is often based on the very arguments that in turn depend on
               lineation. Complicating the matter is that characters do not always speak in full
               lines. Part lines are hard to identify as prose or verse. Multiple short utterances
               by characters speaking in succession may be set on one typographical line.
               Complicating the mise-en-page still further is the fact that prose was often set as
               verse and vice versa to fit text to page space, as well as the fact that, as in
               modern typesetting and digital interfaces, early modern prose lines break where the
               page or column width demands. Line numbers are a common output of a scholarly
               edition. The 1623 first folio of Shakespeare’s plays has even been subjected to a
               copyrighted canonical numbering system (Through Line Numbers). Yet all editorial
               theory since McGann has emphasized the instability of such textual features. Despite
               their utitility for citation and analytical purposes, line numbers can differ wildly
               between editions, precisely because of the difficulty of establishing lines and the
               typographical variations between prose in different formats. The TEI offers three
               ways of encoding lines: we can locate its beginning <gi>lb</gi>, describe it as a
               topographic line <gi>line</gi>, or identify it as a line of verse <gi>l</gi>. We
               discuss the relative merits and implicit critical claims of each encoding method for
               describing and counting lines. We discuss the tension between citable and fluid
               texts, outline how we use the @ed and @edRef attributes in our lineation, and
               introduce our prototype whereby various lineation systems are interoperable. The
               LEMDO (Linked Early Modern Drama) prototype allows for canonical line identifiers,
               but does not foreclose other possibilities; in fact, LEMDO proliferates @xml:ids so
               that projects within the LEMDO ecosystem can make project-level decisions about what
               constitutes a line. Finally, we gesture towards future reconciliation of lineation
               systems through linked-open data.</p>
</body>